does anyone out there ever wonder why
are the glutes so special it's
literally the only muscle that we do low
load activation for prior to the workout
so bro how those airflies treating you
you gonna bench
hold on bro well four i'm doing low low
peg
activation bro low load peck activation
what for i have pectoral amnesia
pectoral amnesia
that's a thing i have dead chest
syndrome dead chest i mean you just made
that up
bro why you gotta be such a dick
so are the glutes really that special
that they require a unique strategy
to prime them for the workout to come or
are we just
obsessed with the glutes and reaching
for reasons to train them differently in
this video i will equip you with the
knowledge
to draw your own conclusion pertaining
to this conundrum
[Applause]
[Music]
so low load glute activation how did it
all come about
i like to think of myself as a historian
strength and conditioning it used to be
a lot easier now with instagram
nobody knows who came up with what it
used to be fairly easy to track things
so i think it can all be traced back to
vladimir yonda now he was a physical
therapist and he was writing about glute
activation
speculating that weak glutes can be
implicated in all kinds of injuries
and failing to rehabilitate them can
cause further issues
now yonder categorized muscles into two
primary categories
you have the tonic muscles that were
prone to tightness
like the hip flexors and you had the
phasic muscles that were prone to
weakness
like the gluteus maximus i used to be
enthralled by all that
now i don't really buy into it that much
but at the time it was fascinating then
you had more physical
therapists talking about weak glutes
like shirley sarman and then a back
rehabilitation specialist known as stu
mcgill
he started writing about it in his book
low back disorders in 2002
and that's what ultimately caused the
strength coaches to take notice so
strength coach mike boyle
in my opinion was the first guy to
really start connecting the pieces
between the physical therapist and then
what we do in the weight room and i
believe he was the first strength coach
to start employing
glute activation drills in his warm-up
prior to the workout and he did so
because
through all the reading he was doing he
says well it's going to prevent anterior
hip pain
it's going to prevent knee issues this
can prevent hamstring and adductor
strains it's going to prevent low back
pain
at this same time that's when it
exploded you know mark verstigan wrote
about in his book
core performance i remember martin
rooney having these crazy glute
activation drills with his
pro athletes he was trained in nfl
football players and he said they could
hardly hang with these easy bodyweight
and band
glute activation exercises you know they
could move five six seven eight hundred
pounds on certain lifts
but they would be destroyed by these
little wimpy glute activation exercise
involving body weight and bands and i
think what really caused it to explode
was when air crescent mike robertson
wrote about it in tnation that was a
very popular website at the time
every strength coach every personal
trainer every serious lift around the
world was reading this site back then
and they wrote a two-part article series
called get your button gear they had you
doing all sorts of hip stretches and
glute activation drills like glute
bridges and bird dogs and fire hydrants
and all of a sudden
without much evidence glute activation
became this buzzword
and the whole industry starts doing it
now i used to bind it and i
i even wrote about it and i would speak
about it in seminars and i felt so smart
i sounded so scientific so follow the
logic here
you're sitting all day long you know
everyone sits in this day and age and
while you're sitting your hip flexors
are shortened so you're causing
adaptive shortening of the hip flexors
now because the hip flexors are
shortened
that's causing the glutes to be weakened
through a process known as
reciprocal inhibition now the glutes are
down regulated
and this leads to what stu mcgill would
call gluteal amnesia which later became
known as
dead butt syndrome now there are three
primary hippic sensors
you've got the gluteus maximus the
hamstrings and the adductors but since
the glutes are now shut down the hammies
and adductors have to work overtime to
pick up the slack for the weakened
glutes now they're overburdened
in a process known as synergistic
dominance which can lead to strain
injuries
now the weak glutes cause problems up
and down the chain
you're unstable you're weak your ankles
are in jeopardy your knees
your hips and even your shoulders
because the glutes transfer all over the
body
now you develop serial distortion
patterns and you're basically a ticking
time bomb
oh it's time to lift
now as you can probably predict i no
longer buy into that whole model
i do agree that the glutes atrophy and
that beginners have
very weak glutes but i think there's a
much simpler explanation i remember in
2008 after the housing market crash
i had to close down my studio and i
wrote an ebook and started blogging for
the first time i was at my computer for
very long hours i was so worried i was
going to develop gluten amnesia
and my glutes would shrink and i'd get
weaker at all my main lifts lo and
behold
i got stronger i was set in prs left and
right why i was used to being on my feet
all day long and i was exhausted
personal training on the gym floor for
10 hours a day
now i went into the weight room feeling
recovered and refreshed and i wasn't so
stale
my glutes actually got stronger and grew
this isn't to say sitting can't harm
your body
i've just always made sure to switch up
my posture and get up and stretch every
once in a while there's an awesome study
one of my favorite papers
published by miyokovic in 2011 in one of
the most prestigious journals the
journal of applied physiology and this
study is kind of hilarious because it
flies in the face of conventional wisdom
this study had a bunch of dudes
confined to complete bed rest for 60
days and it was a six degree downward
tilt because they're
kind of trying to look at the effect of
weightlessness like so it applied to
astronauts like it was for nasa and each
subject had a 24 hour
nurse who would tend to them do all
their hygiene get them food
get them whatever they want and they
just sat in bed now there was another
group that did exercise they would just
do one hard set of the lying squat
machine
you know selectorize with a weight stack
three times a week so one set on say
monday wednesday friday but they utilize
progressive overload so during the 60
days
they got a lot stronger so well over 99
of the time they were
in bed doing nothing only 0.003 percent
of the time were they actually
exercising and lo and behold their
glutes actually grew
why because they got stronger sitting
isn't the culprit
lack of progressive training with the
best glute exercises is the problem i do
believe that in everyday life some
muscles are more prone to weakness than
others
and that's a simple case of use and
disuse based on
activities of daily living think about
climbing stairs
you're gonna use your calves you're
gonna use your quads if you climb two
stairs at a time
your calves and quads get activated
pretty hard
you know even stand up from a chair fill
your quads and stand up from a chair
they develop a lot of tension you know
they get really hard
what do we do in everyday life that gets
our glutes really hard walking stairs
not so much staying up from a chair not
so much taking something off the ground
not so much unless it's really heavy the
things that heavily activate the glutes
are either
consciously activating as hard as
possible well how many people squeeze
their glutes as hard as they can
and do staining glute squeezes every day
no one i know who's not a lifter or
weight training like doing hip thrusts
and squats and deadlifts and lunges
etc or playing sports like sprinting and
jumping which is why volleyball players
for example tend to have decent glute
development
basically the glutes receive less of a
growth stimulus
during activities of daily living than
other muscles such as the quads and the
calves
so they get deconditioned they don't
activate well because they're not used
that much so when you begin lifting
weights you have to gain
coordination but do we need to do low
load glute activation
prior to working out in this video i'm
going to go over what is low load glute
activation i'm going to go over what
does the research say about it
and review the 11 relevant studies on
the topic i'm going to discuss some
personal experiences and anecdotes i'm
going to provide
a sample low load glute activation
workout because i know that that's what
most of you were hoping for in this
video and i'll finish off
with a brief conclusion okay so first
what is low load glute activation here's
what i want you to know it's not a
workout
you know you're not fatiguing yourself
most of us could probably do a hundred
body weight glute bridges in a row
you're not trying to fatigue yourself
you're not trying to do
100 glute bridges right before you do
your squats so you're doing 10
while squeezing your glutes hard you're
trying to prime the muscles you're
trying to stimulate not annihilate
now the theory is by using low loads and
really squeezing the glutes you can
drive
up your activation and cause them to
activate to a greater degree when you
integrate them into more compound
movements like squats and deadlifts
now glute activation should not be
confused
as the mind muscle connection you can
consciously focus on your glutes during
exercise like say you're doing a
hip thrust you can squeeze your glutes
as hard as you can using the mind muscle
connection but this
video is about the dynamic warm-up
that's performed
before a workout hence the title low
load glute activation now there are 11
studies that are worth talking about on
this topic and i'm not going to delve
into them and take forever
even if i spent one minute on each of
them that's 11 minutes
so the first is this paper published by
fisher at allen in 2016.
basically on subjects to do this
movement shown below kind of a band
combined hip extension abduction extra
rotation
and they do 20 minutes three times a day
for a whole week so an
hour of glute activation for a whole
week long and this is really promising
for glute activation what they found
after the week was over that there was
greater excitability in the motor tortex
in the region responsible for activating
the glutes and also less inhibition
so they wanted to do a lot of
concentration on the glutes in a short
amount of time
and they saw actual brain adaptations
and in theory this would transfer into
your exercise because now the brain is
more efficient at activating glutes so
this is a big plus in the glute
activation research now the next one is
by part at all this was published in
this one looked at the effects of a
glute activation warm-up prior to an
explosive hang high pole so basically
you have the bar in the hang position
and you explode up with it and what they
found was
very fascinating by performing the glute
activation prior to the high pole you
actually saw
less glute activation but the same
amount of muscle force
so the authors surmised that they were
primed better
and they're more efficient they didn't
require as much activation to get the
same level of muscle force so that's
another plus
in the glute activation column now the
next paper is by barry at all published
in 2016 and it looked at glute
activation protocols of different rep
ranges
on sprinting acceleration and what they
found was
the 15 rep glute activation group did in
fact see enhanced 10 meter sprinting
performance as long as there's adequate
rest per individual so this is
three straight pluses in favor of glute
activation now the next one is by helium
harrison published in 2014
and what they found was doing a low load
glute activation warm-up
did not enhance single-leg drop jump
performance there were
improvements in performance but those
were due to practice not to glute
activation so this is in the minus
column for glute activation now it's
three to one now the next study is by
cochrane at
all published in 2017 and it looked at a
six-week
glute activation protocol performed
three times a week with bodyweight
exercises and it failed to enhance
glute emg activity or hip extension
force and the authors suggested that
maybe body weight exercises weren't
sufficient enough
to elicit any adaptations so now we're
at three to two
in favor of and against glute activation
the next paper i'm going to discuss
was published by crow at all in 2012.
this was actually the first
gluta activation study i remember
writing about it in a t nation article
it showed that a glute activation
protocol did in fact enhance power
output in the counter movement jump so
now we're at four to two okay now the
next paper is by commons at all
published in 2015 and it showed
that a glute activation protocol did in
fact enhance
jumping output as long as the rest
periods were eight minutes long in
between
the activation warm-up and the jumping
action so now we've got
five studies in support two studies
against now the next paper is by sander
at all published in 2013.
now this paper didn't really look at
glute activation it was just different
types of warm-ups and if i recall
correctly there was a warm-up that
stretched the muscles to longer muscle
lengths and then a workout that was more
conducive with like a low load glute
activation kind of like bridges and
things that work the muscles at shorter
muscle lengths so every dynamic warm-up
includes things like lunges usually and
that's smart because it stretches the
muscle but the more recent trend is to
do things like lateral band rocks glute
bridges these hit the muscles at shorter
lengths and they might not be necessary
and what this study found was that just
doing the traditional exercises that
stretch the muscles to lung muscle
lengths was sufficient adding the more
recent
functional exercises into the mix did
not further enhance
performance so now we're at five to
three all right the next study is by
pinfold at all published in 2018
now this study found that a low load
glute activation warm-up did in fact
enhance jumping and sprinting
performance but it was not due to
increased neural activation so it's
enhancing performance
from some other mechanism so now we're
six to three because it did in fact
enhance performance now the next one is
by harrison mccabe published in 2017
and this study showed that a glute
activation protocol performed prior to
sprinting and jumping did not show an
effect and did not lead to consistent
performing enhancing benefits so now
we're at six to
four in favor and not in favor of low
load glute activation and the last one
is by gallego is
published in 2020 so this study found
that adding
eight weeks of glute activation
exercises as a part of a warm-up led to
significant increases in vertical jump
performance so we have
seven studies in favor of glute
activation
four studies not in favor it doesn't
work that way though like
you don't just say seven to four glute
activation wins a good scientist would
evaluate the entire body of research and
form his opinion based on the strengths
and weaknesses of all of those papers so
i discussed the research
now i'd like to discuss some practical
experience that i have a few things
number one remember when i was testing
emg and sometimes i'd be doing
you know one movement after another
looking at the emg activity of the
glutes and sometimes they'd be so fired
up i'd be walking around i'd just be
walking
and my glute activation would be going
sky high so i always thought that glute
activation works it's like
my glutes are fired up look at how hard
they're firing just from basic
activities but that's not what's been
shown in the research so i became more
skeptical of my own experiments because
i didn't control anything i wasn't
measuring anything directly i was just
looking at the waveform now i have a lot
of
negative experiences with a lot of
lifters
and athletes and clients who took the
whole glute activation thing too far
first of all they'd be performing a
45-minute warm-up before their workouts
you know they'd be fatigued before they
even started lifting weights and second
they would push those low
glute activation exercises too hard you
know again you're just trying to
activate not trying to annihilate the
muscle
if you train your warm up too hard you
will see diminished results in the
weight room but i do have some
powerlifting friends who would swear by
it they would religiously do their
little lateral band walks
they'd do their band glute bridges and
they swore by it they say you know brett
when i do this warm up my hips don't
hurt when i squat
or my low back feels better when i
deadlift and these are guys
pulling you know 750 weighing 200 pounds
what am i going to tell them it's all in
their head i believe them that it helped
but i don't tend to prescribe glute
activation to my clients anymore
i'll get to why i don't in a minute so a
lot of people will google
glute activation workout and you'll find
all these influencers that are happy to
oblige and provide
glute activation workouts if you provide
a glute activation workout
you're proving that you don't understand
what low load glute activation was all
about it's not a workout i'm going to
repeat that it is not a workout you're
just doing activation drills and you are
not getting fatigued
if you're feeling this crazy burn or
getting a pump before the strengthening
workouts you're doing it wrong
nevertheless i will provide you with a
sample low load glute activation series
so starting out you might stretch the
hip flexors you might do like a psoas
stretch and also rectus femoris stretch
then you might do some dynamic stretches
maybe you do some leg swings in
different directions finally you might
do some reverse lunges or just
multi-directional lunges
maybe some goblet squats with light
loads now you're gonna finish it off
with things that activate the glutes but
you're not going anywhere close to
failure you know
you might do 10 lateral band walks you
know 10 to the left 10 to the right
followed by 10 body weight quadruped hip
extensions where you're really squeezing
hard at the top
10 with each leg then you might move
into a band fire hydrant
10 reps and you might finish off with a
10 second
standing glute squeeze or rkc plank
where you're squeezing the glutes as
hard as possible for 10 seconds
you might do that for two rounds so
that's your sample low load glute
activation warm up and i recommend
keeping it very simple just like that
now the conclusion now to wrap
everything up i think the most promising
study to date
in support of low load glute activation
is the fischer paper it showed brain
changes from really concentrating on
activating the glutes in a short period
of time and the sander paper is the
biggest nail in the coffin for low load
glued activation because it showed that
just
doing things like lunges better prepare
the muscles for things like sprinting
and jumping compared to like
glute bridges and lateral bandwalks so
here's my take
yes the fisher paper did show increased
brain efficiency but
in my opinion you get that over time you
know by just doing normal resistance
training the way i do it you know you're
squeezing the glutes during hip thrust
you're focusing on the glutes you're
using the mind muscle connection so over
the course of a couple months
you're going to get all those benefits
anyway but you don't need to spend a lot
of time doing these low load glute
activation you just need to stretch the
muscles during the dynamic warm-up
because you're going to do a lot of
glute exercise if you train the glutes
the way i tell you to now i would like
to direct you to my rule of thirds
video on youtube that i posted about a
month ago you're going to be doing hip
thrust you're going to be doing cable
kickbacks you're going to be doing back
extensions
you're going to do different squat lunge
and hinging movements you're going to be
doing abduction exercises
you're going to be strengthening the
glutes from all vectors
in all different type of rep ranges
hitting all the angles
leaving no stone left unturned but i
hope what you take away from this video
is
someone could cherry pick the studies in
favor of glute activation and make it
look like you're a complete idiot
if you don't employ low load glute
activation as a warm up strategy and
another person could cherry pick the
studies that didn't show a good effect
and make it look like you're an idiot
for employing glute activation so if you
want to be evidence-based
you would want to download all the
studies mentioned in this article
read them evaluate them then you'd want
to experiment on your own do the
warm-ups yourself
and hopefully with clients and athletes
and conduct little experiments see if it
helps
i used to be in favor of low load glute
activation prior to the workout
now i don't i have not seen any
detrimental effects
when i stopped doing them so i don't
think it's necessary
but if you think it's necessary have at
it probably the most important aspect of
this whole video
is to realize that back then when these
guys came up with glute activation
the only popular glute exercise were
vertical in nature
you had your squats your deadlifts your
single leg exercises hip thrust didn't
exist barbell glute bridges didn't exist
west side was doing like reverse hypers
and back extensions
and cable pull throughs but they hadn't
really reached mainstream yet mark bell
hadn't come out with his hip circles yet
so no hip circles no glute loops
no athletes weren't doing cable hip
abductions or the seated hip abduction
machine really it was only vertical hip
extension exercises
so these guys kind of came up with the
whole multi-vectorial glute training
system
without even knowing it they started
doing glute activation it was always
horizontal vector
or lateral rotary vector it was do these
single leg glute bridges
do these bird dogs do these x-band walks
or or monster walks or sumo walks so
these were amazing at the time
glute activation in this regard was
revolutionary the problem is when i came
along we
really pushed the horizontal training
vector forward soon after that a lot of
other coaches got in on the works we
started come up with
every variation under the sun for all
the hip thrust and glute bridge
variations and then we started coming
with more bands
the cloth bands like the hip circles now
we have strengthening exercises why
would you settle for activation
movements when you can do strengthening
movements
eventually the industry's doing all the
bridges and thrusts we're doing tons of
abduction movements we're doing
rotational movements and in my opinion
this rendered glute activation obsolete
but even though the industry evolved
what these physical therapists and
strength coaches did should not be
underappreciated
they laid the foundation for better
glute training so some coaches still
cling to the glute activation concept
but to me we're strengthening every
vector in the exercises that we normally
do if you like what you saw in this
video
please make sure you hit like please
leave a comment and definitely make sure
you're subscribed to my channel
i've got a lot of great things to come
in 2021. now if this video intrigued you
and you would like to train under my
system using my principles
then i invite you to click on the link
below and subscribe to booty by brett
and join the thousands of other happy
members who are seeing amazing results